# 72年 国宴上 银耳汽锅鸡
Steam Pot Chicken with White Wood Mushroom at 1972 Chinese State Banquet
# 大爷可以吃了 快点你一吃
Da ye, go have a try.
# 保证大家都回去做去
I am sure everyone wants to give a shot at home
# 炖银耳汽锅鸡的这种鸡最好用雏母鸡
It’s the best to cook with pullet
# 没下过蛋的母鸡
Hen that has never laid any egg before
# 这是一个宫廷黄鸡
This is an “Royal Chick”
# 这鸡怎么去骨
How to remove the bones?
# 从脊背开一刀 然后两个腿分开
Open up the back with knife and pull the chicken legs apart
# 拿刀尖搁在这儿往下一拽
Point the blade here and pull the legs
# 鸡腿下来了
Here we go. The legs get pulled off
# 翅膀上有一个关节
Here you can see a joint on wing
# 也就是我们说的翅根儿
Which is what we called “Chicken Drumette”
# 刀进去 刀尖正好窝到这个窝里头
Insert the tip of knife inside and make sure the tip is right inside the notch
# 拿手一硌 按着 往下一拽就行了
Press and push the knife and you can pull off the wing easily
# 下来了
There you go
# 鸡牙子 有的叫鸡里脊
“Ji Ya Zi” which is also called “Chicken Fillet”
# 往下一别 拿刀尖你看着啊
Pull it down. Take a look. We’ll use the tip of knife
# 大妈给照细着点
Da ma, make sure you have a closer look on it
# 因为这有一根筋 拿刀
Because there is a tendon, use knife
# 剌一刀 硌着 拿刀尖一扥 下来了
cut through and peel it off.
# 这就是那里脊
This is the chicken fillet
# 两个 这边来一刀
We got two. Same cut goes to the other side
# 因为它这边有好多小筋膜
It got some fasciae over there
# 走 两根儿 这鸡架子就没用了
There we go. Two pieces. We don’t need the skeleton anymore
# 鸡架子要多的话我们可以熬汤
We can make chicken broth if we have extra skeleton
# 这个就没用了 浪费啦
Are we gonna throw it? What a waste!
# 浪费不了 熬汤啊
No, we can make broth
# 你看鸡牙子里头 筋
You see the fillet has a lot of tendons
# 拿手指头摁住了 使劲就下来了 一推
Hold it with your fingers.  Press and push it
# 下面开始剔 怎么剔 就三下两下的
Now we are going to remove the meat. Pretty easy.
# 翅根 给一刀
At the bottom end of wing drumette. Cut through
# 翅中这儿 给一刀
Wing flat. Cut through.
# 这都是关节 都是关节
They are all joints
# 你看一顶
Easily push it out
# 你看翅中这儿 这点轻轻给一刀
Look at the wing flat. Knock it slightly
# 拿刀一别 拿刀尖 这刀尖很有用
Push it outward with your knife and then use the knife tip. The tip of knife is pretty useful.
# 干净不干净
So clean, right?
# 一点肉都没有 还真是干干净净的
No more meat left. That’s amazing.
# 翅尖就不用了 这都去熬汤了
We don’t need the wing tip. All go into the soup
# 这鸡胸肉剔完了
We are done with the chicken breast
# 鸡腿肉 因为这只鸡来的时候是盘着的
Chicken legs. Since the chicken was folded when we got it,
# 这只关节上有点断了
the joint was kind of broken
# 鸡腿肉弄好了 按着这骨节儿
Flat the chicken leg. Hold the ankle.
# 刀
Use the knife
# 一滑
rub
# 这骨头全露出来了 这有个关节
Here comes out the bone. There is a joint
# 一别 太费劲了
Push. That’s too hard.
# 剔这只鸡用多长时间
How long will it take to cut the whole chicken?
# 那时候我们搞比赛的时候
When I was in a competition,
# 对你们那时候比赛过
I remember that you’ve participated one before
# 五十秒 就能剔完了
Within only 55 seconds
# 所有的骨头就都离开了
All bones are off
# 咱们今天因为给网友展示
Because we need to show to our youtube users
# 速度稍微慢一点 让网友看清楚一点
We have to do it slower to make sure it’s clear enough to follow
# 实在看不清怎么办 就买去就行了
What if it’s not clear enough? Just go out and buy one
# 这有根牙签骨 紧贴着 很细
Here is a Fibula. Attached. Thin
# 这叫牙签骨 拿刀压住了这骨头
It’s called “fibula”. Hold the bones with knife
# 也是给它扥下来
Pull it out
# 这是它的关节骨头 它不是肉
This is bone not meat
# 牙签骨在这儿呢
This is the fibula
# 看见了很细
So thin
# 整个的鸡就剔完了
So we are all done with the whole chicken
# 剔完了我们要检查有些小的
We need to do a final check
# 可能还有些小骨头 摸一摸
There might be some small pieces of bones
# 切干净 都干净了
All should be cleaned out
# 银耳汽锅鸡咱们给它改改刀啊
Let’s trim the chicken
# 排排刀 这叫排 排刀
Scoring. This is called “scoring”
# 腿儿上筋多 刀尖硌一下
Chicken legs have more fasciae. Use knife tip to break it
# 筋再给它斩一斩
Break the fasciae
# 鸡胸肉也是
So does the chicken breast
# 摸摸这地方有小骨头没有
Feel if there are small pieces of bones
# 你看这 有
There is
# 给它去了
Trim it off
# 排排刀等于一会儿一传热
Scoring it
# 跟小球似的
It will form like a ball once it’s heated
# 鸡肉没有切的 全是剁
We don’t “cut” chicken we “chop” it
# 因为它切着有筋 不好切 这叫鸡块
The fasciae make it hard to cut. This is called chicken nuggets
# 搁一盆里
Put all in one bowl
# 黄酒
Huangjiu (rice wine)
# 盐 还是那句话 咱家盐不咸
Salt. The salt I’m using is not that salty.
# 多搁点 两勺
So more. Two tablespoons
# 淀粉 淀粉有玉米淀粉
Starch. Corn starch
# 咱家这个就是玉米淀粉
We’re using corn starch
# 有白薯粉 有土豆粉 有绿豆淀粉
There are sweet potato starch, potato starch and green bean starch.
# 这个淀粉用哪个最好
Which is the best?
# 就是玉米淀粉 绿豆淀粉
Corn starch or mung bean starch
# 像有的生粉（不适合） 太黏了
Some, like potato starch, are not good for it. Too sticky
# 蛋清 一个鸡蛋的蛋清 用不了
Egg white of one egg. No need to use all.
# 所以有时候我们有好多网友炒菜
So sometimes when we make stir fries
# 说怎么老粘锅 不是锅的问题
People are asking why food always stick to the pan. It’s not because of the pan
# 是料不够 不是 料多了 蛋清太多
It’s not because of the lack of ingredients.  It’s because we have too many ingredients. Too much egg white.
# 我们给它上浆
Tenderize the meat with starch and egg white
# 前些日子介绍过水滑 油滑
We have introduced “cook in water” and “cook in oil” in our previous video
# 因为咱们是炖汤 就要水滑
We need to “cook in water” this time because we are making soup
# 炖汤 不要那么多油
You do not want too much oil when you make soup
# 这个出来以后特别清淡
This way your soup will be fresh and light
# 浆的是以什么为标准 一个是上劲了
How to know that the meat is well-tenderized. Tip 1 is that you can feel the drag when you sir it
# 黏糊了 也说明这淀粉全覆在肉上了
Number two, it looks sticky which means the meat is all covered by starch
# 水滑的时候
When we cook meat in water
# 这淀粉略微的要比炒菜的淀粉
We need a little bit more starch than we use for stir fries
# 略微的多一点
A little bit more
# 因为它在水里它要分解一部分
This is because it will dissolve some into water
# 这个不用拿油封 炒菜可以拿油封上
Don’t need to add oil in. If you want to make stir fries you can add some oil.
# （用油封）下锅容易散（不易粘连）
Meat can fall apart easily (not stick together) in the pot with oil
# 这个就不用了是吧
We don’t use oil this time
# 忘了 白胡椒
I forgot! Add white pepper powder
# 这银耳我们有的人爱吃冰糖银耳
Some people like eating white wood mushroom with white rock sugar
# 冰糖银耳别老早放冰糖
Don’t put sugar too early
# 白糖冰糖都不能早放 后放
No matter what sugar it is
# 先把银耳蒸烂 然后再放冰糖再蒸
Get the white wood mushroom cooked first. Then add sugar and steam again.
# 那银耳蒸出来以后软糯滑
This way the white wood mushroom will be super smooth
# 我们在涨发干货的时候 不要用热水
Do not use hot water to re-hydrate dried food
# 太急 你说木耳银耳 就凉水早点泡
Don’t rush. You can start earlier with cold water
# 提前两三个小时给它泡上
Re-hydrate it two or three hours in advance
# 这干货的东西
For dried food
# 一定要用凉水让它慢慢回软
You have to use cold water to re-hydrate it slowly
# 咱们等锅的功夫
While we are waiting for water boiled
# 给大家展示展示我们的汽锅
I wanna show our steam pot
# 那天我实话说咱们搬家的时候
Honestly, when we moved
# 我差点给它扔了
I almost threw it away
# 看啊 我掀盖儿了啊
Look at it! I’ll open the lid
# 网友们注意 大汽锅
Attention please: large steam pot!
# 这个汽锅到目前为止
It’s has been 50 years
# 我拿到手里 五十年
Since I got it
# 前边有多少年我就不知道了
I don’t know how many years before I got it
# 听听这声
Hear the echo
# 脆
Clink
# 这是我们的大汽锅
This is our large steam pot
# 还有小汽锅 这小汽锅有意思
We also got a small size steam pot. This pot is pretty interesting
# 以前就是紫砂 现在改成白砂
It used to be made of purple sand and nowadays it’s made of white sand
# 这也挺精致的 这是每人一位的
Looks delicate. One per person.
# 开锅烫银耳
Cook white wood mushroom with boiled water
# 其实在家里头如果没有汽锅
If you don’t have steam pot at home
# 我们就找一个 汤蛊子
You can find a soup pot as substitute
# 圆锅蒸带盖的
Round pot with lid
# 把这些料都装好了圆锅一蒸
Put ingredients all inside the pot and steam
# 不用等它开 烫一下就行 有个三五分钟
Don’t need to wait water to boil again. 3 to 5 five minutes are enough
# 也不用去冲凉
Don’t need use cold water to cool down
# 下面就着这水
Now we will still use the water
# 这个肉下锅的时候别动它
Don’t stir meat once you put meat in the pot
# 用水慢慢把它拖熟 散开放
Use water to cook it. Put it in separately
# 它在不断的有变化
It’s changing continuously
# 它是一球一球的
They are separate chicken cubes
# 一动不要紧那淀粉就下来
Don’t touch it or the starch will get off
# 就是因为你给它 排刀
Because you scored the meat
# 排刀以后它经过一紧 就变成球了
Once it’s heated, the meat will contract and roll into ball.
# 稍微攉拢一下
Stir slightly
# 现在攉拢可以 现在定型了
Right now, you can stir it because the shape of chicken is fixed
# 只要你分着撒进去 它不会粘在一起
As long as you throw the meat in separately, they wouldn’t stick together
# 这也要开吗 要开
Do we need to wait until water boil? Yes, we do
# 要全熟 淀粉全部都凝固
Has to be fully cooked and starch solidifies.
# 出来以后它这个汤会稍微有点黏
The texture of soup could be a little bit thick
# 我们捞出这鸡还要拿凉水
We will put the chicken under cold running water once we take it out
# 冲冲表面的浮沫
Wash away the scum
# 这就好了
There we go
# 然后我端过来 给我们网友看 倍儿白
I can show you guys. So clean.
# 我们看看 倍儿干净
Look at it. So clean
# 是一个一个的小球球 鸡球
Looks like little balls. Chicken balls
# 我洗洗它 好冲一下
Let me wash it. Right, rinse it
# 冲出来更漂亮 看看 倍儿利索
It looks better. Look at it. Perfect.
# 现在我们就开始给它装汽锅了
Now we are gonna put them in these steam pots.
# 你看这个家里人吃还可以小一点
Chicken can be cut into small cubes for home-made serving
# 但是宴会你看这大汽锅
But for banquet it is too small for this large steam pot
# 块太小了就不行了
Too small for large party
# 像这小汽锅 你看几块
How many cubes in each small steam pot?
# 两块 就搁两块 一个人吃两块不少
Two, just two. Enough.
# 因为还有银耳 银耳
Because we also get white wood mushroom
# 你看这里边 一片姜
Look. A slice of ginger
# 都是单着放 要是这小锅就得单着放
One by one. Has to be precise for this small pot
# 因为我们没有吊汤
We didn’t make broth this time
# 要如果是高档宴会
But if for high-end banquet
# 我们还要吊点清汤
We need to make broth
# 像刚才鸡架子 吊点汤
Make broth with the chicken skeleton
# 这两个小锅就好了
All done with these two small pots
# 因为咱家蒸锅有点小 条件有限
Because we only have small steamer at home
# 用一个不锈钢盆
We will use this stainless-steel bowl instead of the large steam pot
# 这个大小合适
This fit
# 看着啊 放进去
Look. Put it in
# 银耳
And wood mushroom
# 枸杞
Goji berry
# 这小锅一个里边两个
Two goji berries for each small pot
# 大妈回头把蒸锅给点上 开火
Dama go turn on the stove top and place the steamer on the burner.
# 葱放多少得记着 姜放多少得记着
You have to remember the exact numbers of slices of scallions and gingers you put
# 到时候得往出拣 取出来
Because you have to take them out later
# 葱段姜片搁浮头
Put scallions and gingers on top
# 因为咱们来不及吊汤 咱就使开水
It’s too late to make broth so we will be using boiled water instead.
# 这要是有鸡汤更好了 清鸡汤
It’s better to cook with chicken broth, fresh clean chicken broth.
# 这里边得搁点东西 调味啊
We need to season it
# 酒 这个多一点
Wine. The more the better.
# 盐 别太多 多不了这是汤
Salt. Don’t add too much. It won’t be salty. This is soup.
# 那也多不了
It won’t be anyway
# （白）胡椒
White pepper powder
# 调一汤
Season the water
# 这汤我们要定一下味 定好了味了
Make the soup flavored
# 确实有味 呛着我了
It is. I smelled it
# 看着 灌上
Look. Fill it in
# 这小锅不少装
The small pot can hold a lot
# 剩下这汤倒这里
Pour the soup into it
# 你看这一搁黄酒  好的黄酒
Look at it with good “huangjiu” (rice wine)
# 我们给它搁到锅底儿
Put it at the bottom of the stemaer
# 这个搁到上头 盖上盖
Put them on top and place the lid
# 蒸一小时 一小时呢
Steam for 1 hour. Wow 1 hour
# 锅一会就开 咱们就先蒸上
The steamer will be ready soon so let’s start right now
# 到点了 热气腾腾的
Time’s up. Steam burst
# 拿出来 勺儿 碟儿
Take it out! Spoon and Plate.
# 咱还有大的呢
We also got a larger one
# 把葱姜拣了 四片姜 四段葱
Take the scallion and ginger out. Four ginger slices and four scallion slices
# 都在这浮头呢
All on top
# 你看那银耳也软活了吧
The wood mushroom is soft either
# 这锅我再烫一下 真讲究
Pour into this pot. You are so fastidious.
# 闻着香不香 清香清香的
Smell it. Smell so good and fresh.
# 真好 这就是你一盅我一盅
Sweet. One for you and one for myself
# 你看看  真是热乎乎的
Look at it. Hot.
# 你先吃怎么样 给我们说说
Have a taste. How is it?
# 汤极鲜 为什么鸡是鲜的 原汤原味
It’s tasty. Why? Because the chicken is fresh. The soup is cooked just out of a whole chicken
# 再加上我们用清炖的方法 不油腻
Plus, we simmer without oil. It’s not oily
# 银耳软烂 鸡块也软烂 清香
Both wood mushroom and chicken are soft and pulpy
# 还有枸杞
And goji berries
# 一会大妈也品尝一个 一会我也喝
Da ma, have a taste. I’ll try either.
# 家有大厨 就是幸福
So glad to have my master chef at home!